בוקר טוב Boker tov later. בוקר
טוב. Boker tov. Today's דף Daf is דף ד Daf daled and
we are transitioning into a little bit of a digression, a little
fun digression because the גמרא Gemara was
discussing the minimum height of a wall once you're building this wall,
question whether it's because you're forced to because of היזק ראיה, Hezek
reiyah, because you agree to and how high does a wall out
of stone have to be to be four אמות, Amot, how wide
does it have to be to support that height and the גמרא
Gemara then started asking well then how come the wall of the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash could be so high even if it was
not significantly wider? So that introduced the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, the
building of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and the second בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash and that
is where now working up to bring that back in and we
started by discussion of another type of discussion about building, about can
you tear down a שול Shul in order to build another one
or generally you can't for two different reasons, one because there won't
be a place to pray in the interim and the other is
because you might be negligent and never get around to doing
it. And there were some interesting discussions about possible exceptions to that
rule yesterday. So now we pick up how that discussion is going
to bring us back to the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash discussion. So
we're on ג עמוד ב Gimmel amud beis and we are
at the
first wide line, end of the first wide line on ג עמוד
ב. Gimmel amud beis. בבא בן בוטא, Bava Ben Buta, בבא בן
בוטא Bava Ben Buta who we will find out is the name
of a תנא Tanna who lived in the time of the second
בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, a rabbi lived in the time of the
second בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash who according to חזל Chazal played a
role in advising Herod in the building in the rebuilding of the
second
בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Obviously there was a second בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash prior to Herod but Herod rebuilt it in this magnificent way.
היכי אספיה ליה עצה להורדוס למיסתריה לבית המקדש? Heichi aspirei lei eitza
leHordus lemisterei leBeis Hamikdash? How did he give advice to Herod to
tear down the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and to build a nicer
one in its place? ואמר רב חסדא לא ליסתור איניש בי כנישתא
עד דבני בי כנישתא אחריתי. V'amar Rav Chisda lo listarei inish beis
knishta ad dbanei beis knishta achrita. Didn't he know the פסק, Psak,
didn't he know the הלכה? Halacha? You're not supposed to tear down
a בית כנסת Beis Knesset until you build another one. Now of
course we will see, it's a funny question because first of all
here's a place where there's no alternative because you have to build
it in the same place. If there's any time you need the
same plot of land to build a building, it's in the case
of the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. So what really is your alternative?
The other funny thing about this is that
it never occurred to
me, historically speaking as opposed to in the context of this גמרא,
Gemara, that when they were building the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, what
did we think, did they think that rebuilding it in the time
of Herod, did they do it in a way that they couldn't
continue functioning as they were building it? Was there a period of
time in the improving, the enlarging of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash
that they weren't bringing
קרבנות? Korbanot? I imagined they found a way, you rebuild section at
a time and whatever and you find a way you can even
bring קרבנות Korbanot even if there aren't the walls, מקריבים אף על
פי שאין בית. Makrivim af al pi she-ein bayit. So the fact
that there's an assumption it sounds like they stopped, now maybe not,
maybe the גמרא Gemara assumes that even if you can keep on,
even if there is a place to דאוון, Daven, there's a question
about פשיעה Pshia about negligence, you won't get around to rebuilding
it. But anyway, that's a second question I have: what are we
supposed to imagine happened when they were rebuilding it in the time
of Herod? Were they being able to continue bring קרבנות Korbanot or
not? That's not clear. How much did they totally knock it down?
Did they do it in sections? How did they exactly do it?
But the sense that the גמרא Gemara has is that it was
pretty disruptive and so that's number
two. Number three is of course the fact which I find fascinating
is the fact that it just calls it a בית כנסת. Beis
Knesset. Like the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash is a big בית כנסת
Beis Knesset and that's also very interesting, it's almost like the rabbinic
retrojecting of their reality onto the previous time. So we're going to
sort of see that continue in terms of the sense of how
much was the dominant religious authorities at that time sort of the
rabbis or the כהנים Kohanim and that also we often get a
sense of through the rabbinic lens that it's like the rabbis were
the dominant authorities even in the time of the בית המקדש. Beis
Hamikdash. So in a way you have this by playing let's just
apply this rabbinic law that got formulated later about בית כנסת Beis
Knesset and go ahead and ask it about how they did this
thing with the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, almost defining the בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash or categorizing it as a type of a בית כנסת.
Beis Knesset. So that's the גמרא's Gemara question: how did he go
ahead and give him this
advice? עד דבני בי כנישתא אחריתי? Ad dbanei beis knishta achrita? So
the גמרא Gemara says איבעית אימא תיוהא חזא ביה, Ibayei teima tivya
chaza bei, maybe it's like the thing we said before, they found
cracks and breaks and it was the old one was falling apart,
so that gave them special license to do it. איבעית אימא Ibayei
teima and if you want מלכותא שאני, Malchuta shani, no, if it's
a decision of the government of the king then we're not concerned
about it. because, you know, once a king passes the edict, you
don't have to be concerned about negligence, you know that it's going
to get done. דאמר שמואל de'amar Shmuel because שמואל Shmuel says אי
אמר מלכותא עקרנא טורי ei amar malchusa akrana turi if the king
were to say I'll uproot a mountain עקרנא טורי ולא הדרי akrana
turi velo hadrei they'll find a way to uproot the mountain and
they won't retract it. I mean, you know, they do that sometimes:
they build tunnels through mountains, they level mountains or whatever, you know,
for construction. So anyway, so kings have all of the resources at
their disposal and therefore we do not have to worry...
is it a
new king then it doesn't matter? That's true, but anyway, that's the
גמרא's Gemara's various answers to this question. But again, it does raise
those interesting issues about: are we supposed to imagine that during this
period, you know, were they still using that location or not? But
again there were two concerns about rebuilding: one was where you have
a place to continue to pray or here to do the עבודה,
avodah, and the other is will there be negligence and you won't
get around to rebuilding it. Yes Rabbi Dov?
Do you think at all you're inserting sort of a הלכה'דיק halachic
quandary in right how could they have done this?
The גמרא Gemara is, yeah.
Right the גמרא Gemara is, so do you think that
עקרנא טורי akrana turi has like you're hinting like עוקר הרים oker
harim like it's a משל, mashal, like it's a play on...
yeah that is true, I mean the whole phrase of עוקר הרים
oker harim is a, you know, is a sort of rabbinic description
about the... yeah, so it's an interesting question. Yeah.
I mean with ישיבה yeshiva days so a profound lack of Jewish
history, so I'm, you know, I'm just trying to understand:
is the גמרא Gemara viewing that הורדוס Hordos built the second בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash over the ruins of the first?
No no no no, he he the second one was built at
the time of, you know, עזרא נחמיה Ezra Nechemya whatever, but it
was a it was a smaller more modest structure, right, and that's
why the גמרא Gemara said before גדול יהיה כבוד הבית הזה האחרון
מן הראשון, gadol yihiyeh kevod habayis hazeh ha'acharon min harishon, that eventually
it became bigger than the first בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash at the
time of הורדוס. Hordos. הורדוס Hordos did a you know... now, did
he do it by knocking fully knocking down the second and rebuilding
the other one?
He leveled the top of הר הבית.
Har Habayis. Oh that's true, I'm remembering this.
He completely leveled the top of הר הבית. Har Habayis.
Yeah yeah you're right.
To create built retaining walls of which the כותל Kotel is one,
filled it in with soil on all three on three out of
four sides...
right right right.
And then rebuilt a huge
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash around...
yeah
yeah yeah now I'm remembering that I mean...
so he really did move...
they moved out, they moved out for a short... so that's a
very good point and thank you for reminding me about that, like
I said, I just I just was in ירושלים Yerushalayim and I
took the tunnel tour for like the fifth time but I had
forgotten that point which is very relevant for us. So thank you
for reminding, which is that's true, is that he didn't only reconstruct
the building but, like you know, there's like the flat top of
the הר הבית Har Habayis which allows for that huge plaza is
not a natural formation, you know, he did that. Actually maybe that
also is very relevant to this עקרנא טורי akrana turi to this
uprooting mountains because that's really what he did, is that he completely
moved an enormous amount of earth to reconstruct the mountain to create
this flat plaza. So I thank you Rabbi Dov for reminding us
of that so it really is true, you know. So what did
they do during that...
it's open for renovations I mean like...
I understand but besides that the question still is is that where
were they מקריב קרבנות makriv korbanos during that time? Were they on
a pause, on a hiatus? Anyway so that really heightens the גמרא's
Gemara's question. Okay, so let's see where the גמרא Gemara goes. Let's
see where the... but thank you you're right they actually did completely
destroy everything that was there. So the גמרא Gemara says like this,
okay, הורדוס עבדא דבי חשמונאי הוה. Hordos avda de'bei Chashmonai hava.
Now how was this הורדוס Hordos how did he get to be
king? Because, you know, it was the חשמונאים Chashmonaim that were king
before him, so he was a slave in the house of the
חשמונאי Chashmonai הוה. hava. נתן עיניו בההיא תינוקת nasan einav behahi tinoskas
and he put, you know, cast his eyes on this young woman,
like he had this lust for one of the one of the
daughters of the חשמונאים. Chashmonaim. יומא חד שמע yoma chad shama and
one day he heard, where he heard it from a heavenly voice
people or you know some type of people saying something some type
of voice saying... excuse me no it is a בת קול. bas
kol. יומא חד שמע הוא גברא בת קול yoma chad shama hu
gavra bas kol one day this person, you know, that הורדוס Hordos
heard this בת קול bas kol which normally is understood as a
heavenly voice although again Saul Lieberman says that sometimes it just means
like an echo or a rumor but presumably here it means a
heavenly voice. One time, one day the הורדוס Hordos heard a בת
קול bas kol דאמר כל עבדא דמריד השתא מצלח, de'amar kol avda
de'marid hashta matzlach, any slave that rebels today will be successful. So
he says: Great, here's my opportunity and now I can, you know,
marry that that girl that I was in that that I'm lusting
after. So it's interesting, it makes it more about sex than about
power in terms of his primary drive to do what he
did. קם קטלינהו לכולהו מרוותיה, kam katlinhu le'khulu marosei,
he got up, he he killed all of his masters, the whole
house of the חשמונאים, Chashmonaim, ושיירי לההיא ינוקא veshayrei lehahi yanuka and
he left the one woman he the one he left was that
young woman so that because he was lusting after, maybe also that
would legitimize his power because now he's married to
a, you
know, to
somebody from the חשמונאים... Chashmonaim... in order that he would become the
next king. I'm serious, there is an actual historical case like that.
Anyway, okay. כי חזיא ההיא ינוקתא דקא בעי למינסבה, ki chazya hahee
yenuksa deka baei leminsava,
when that young woman saw that he was now going to try
to marry her, סליקא לאיגרא, slika leigra, she went up to the
rooftop, ורמא קלא, verama kala, she shouted out, raised her voice, אמרה,
amra, she said, כל מאן דאתי ואמר מבית חשמונאי קאתינא, kol man
de'ati ve'amar mibeis Chashmonai kasina,
anybody who is going to claim in the future that they come
from the בית חשמונאי, Beis Chashmonai, עבדא הוא, avda hu, they are
a liar, they are really a slave, דלא אישתייר מינייהו, delo ishtayer
minaihu, the only true descendant of the בית חשמונאי Beis Chashmonai that
remains אלא ההיא ינוקתא, ela hahee yenuksa, this young woman, meaning myself.
וההיא ינוקתא נפלה מאיגרא לארעא, vehahee yenuksa nafla meigra le'ara, and this
young woman fell from the roof to the floor, to the ground,
and she basically threw herself off the roof. So basically, he was
trying to legitimize his power and she made this announcement that his
power is illegitimate and he is not going at all connected to
the true house of the חשמונאים. Chashmonaim. That is an individual reflection
of the downfall.
What? It is a visual reflection of the downfall. A downfall of
the house? That is a good point, yeah.
Okay, טמנה שבע שנין, tamna sheva shanin, now what Herod did is
he preserved her body, literally buried her for seven years בדובשא, beduvsha,
in honey, some type of a preservative. Now why was he doing
this? איכא דאמרי בעלה, ika de'amri ba'ala, he did it so he
could basically have intercourse with her even after she was dead. איכא
דאמרי לא בעלה, ika de'amri lo ba'ala, he did not. דאמרי לא
בעלה, de'amri lo ba'ala, those that say he did not, הא דטמנה
לסויי ליצריה, ha detamna lesuyei leyitzrei, in order to satisfy his lust,
so that was presumably the driving force here altogether. ודאמרי לה לא
בעלה, ved'amri lah lo ba'ala, and those that say that he did
not have intercourse with her, הא דטמנה, ha detamna, so why did
he preserve her body? כי היכי דנימרו בת מלך נסב, ki heichi
denimru bas melech nasav, so to get legitimacy for his reign, that
people would think that he is still married to her. Look, she
is not feeling great today, but take a look at her. Okay,
anyway. אמר מאן דריש, amar man darish, now that is how he
seized power. Okay, then stage number two. He said, מאן דריש מקרב
אחיך תשים עליך מלך, man darish mikerev achicha tasim aleicha melech, who
are those that explicate this verse that you should only have a
king from amongst your brethren, והא דמיעט למדידי עבדא, veha demi'at lemididi
avda, and that that would exclude me, a slave? So now he
is working to further legitimize his power. רבנן, rabbanan, it is the
rabbis. So now again we have in the time of the second
בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, the rabbis are the ones that have the
real religious power. This is again they are retrojecting later realities. Okay.
תוספות Tosafos by the way says, why do you need the rabbis
to דרוש darosh and it is an explicit פסוק? posuk? But it
says no, because from the פסוק posuk you could have excluded non-Jews.
But the rabbis say you even exclude slaves. Slaves have a partial
obligation in מצוות, mitzvos, but the rabbis say that slaves are excluded
from this verse as well. So it is all the rabbis' fault.
Is he not now a free slave? He is not, that is
an interesting question, if somebody who all their masters died, but all
Jews are related, so ultimately somebody must have inherited him. It might
not be from a בית חשמונאי Beis Chashmonai house. Alright. So he
freed himself. Okay. קם קטלינהו לכולהו רבנן, kam katlinu lechulu rabbanan, he
slaughtered all the rabbis.
Now תוספות Tosafos says that is not really true because there were
what do you call it, there were other, we know rabbis from
the time if you look at תוספות, Tosafos, קטלינהו לכולהו רבנן לאו
דווקא לכולהו, katlinu lechulu rabbanan lav davka lechulu, not all of them,
דהא בני בתירא שהיו נשיאים כשעלה הלל מבבל, deha bnei Beseira shehayu
nesi'im kesha'ala Hillel miBavel, when הלל Hillel came from בבל, Bavel, which
was not long after this, there were still the בני בתירא, Bnei
Beseira, etc. etc. Okay, anyway, but he killed off the vast majority
of the rabbis. שבקה לבבא בן בוטא, shavkei leBava ben Buta, the
one he left behind was בבא בן בוטא. Bava ben Buta. למישקל
עצה מיניה, lemishkal eiza minei, he thought that that guy was a
smart guy, he did not want to kill them all off, maybe
this guy would be good to keep him as his advisor. I
think it stopped. Alright. אחזי ליה כלילא דסילא, ahazei lei klila desila,
fine, he kept בבא בן בוטא Bava ben Buta around. So he
put on בבא בן בוטא Bava ben Buta a type of a
crown with thorns pointing inward, ונקרינהו לעיניה, venakrinhu le'einei, and he used
that as a way of basically poking out his eyes. I do
not know why he had to do it through this crown, and
obviously there is maybe some symbolism here that he is wearing a
crown.
But anyway, he is taking
leadership. Not every century that would have the image of somebody wearing
a crown of thorns. No. Alright, that is a good point. With
thorns pointed inwards towards the eyes, but that is a good point,
the crown of thorns. Okay. נקרינהו לעיניה. nakrinhu le'einei. יומא חד אתא
ויתיב קמיה, yoma chad asa veyasiv kamei, so now he has got
this blind surviving rabbinic. figure who he wants as his advisor. Now
one day because he came and he sat in front of him
and he didn't Herod and he didn't present himself as Herod, so
and the guy was blind, so the assumption was he didn't realize
who Herod was, you know that this was Herod in front of
him. אמר amar and he said, חזי מר האי עבדא בישא מאי
קא עביד, chazi mar hai avda bisha mai ka avid, then interesting
immediate use of visual imagery.
Have you seen this, this evil slave, what he's doing?
Meaning he was presenting himself as some commoner and talking to him
and saying, can you imagine this, this slave who now thinks that
he's king? He wanted to see how this Rabbi would respond, how
loyal he would be. אמר ליה, amar leh, מאי אעביד ליה? mai
avid leh? What do you want me... so okay, but what do
you want me to do about it? אמר ליה, amar leh, נלטייה
מר, niltayeh mar, why not curse him? נלטייה מר, niltayeh mar, why
not curse him? אמר ליה, amar leh, כתיב, ketiv, גם במדעך מלך
אל תקלל, gam bemada'acha melech al tekalel, even in your sort of
private chamber, don't curse a king. No, we have to respect the
king, we can't curse him. אמר ליה, amar leh, האי לאו מלך
הוא, hai lav melech hu, yeah, he's not a real king. אמר
ליה, amar leh, ויהא עשיר בעלמא, ve'i havei ashir be'alma, so what,
even if he doesn't really deserve to be king, let him just
be a very wealthy powerful person. וכתיב, u'khetiv, ובחדרי משכבך אל תקלל
עשיר, u'vechadrei mishkavcha al tekalel ashir, don't curse a wealthy person. You
shouldn't go around cursing people even if I'm not happy with it.
ולא יהא אלא נשיא, velo yehei ela nasi, and anyway, even if
he's not a king, he's still a leader. וכתיב, u'khetiv, ונשיא בעמך
לא תאר, venasi ve'amecha lo ta'or, don't curse a nasi, a prince
amongst your people. אמר ליה, amar leh, so this, so Herod, who
was like, you know, obviously in disguise as it were, said back
to him, בעושה מעשה עמך, be'oseh ma'aseh amcha, okay, but that's נשיא
בעמך nasi be'amcha when he's acting like a member of your tribe,
not when he's not acting like a member of your tribe, not
when he's doing these evil deeds. So you should still curse him.
אמר ליה, amar leh, מסתפינא מיניה, mistafina minei, no, I'm afraid of
him. I want, I'm still not, I'm not going to do it.
אמר ליה, amar leh, ליכא אינש דאזיל דלימא ליה דאנא ואת יתיבנא.
leika inash de'azil de'leima leh de'ana ve'at yativna. What? Michael just wait.
Okay. אמר ליה, amar leh, ליכא אינש דאזיל דלימא ליה דאנא ואת
יתיבנא. leika inash de'azil de'leima leh de'ana ve'at yativna. There's nobody who'll
tell him that we're sitting here. What are you afraid of? It's
just the two of us, nobody else is around. אמר ליה, amar
leh, כתיב, ketiv, no, כי עוף השמים יוליך את הקול ובעל כנפים
יגיד דבר, ki of hashamayim yolich et hakol u'va'al knafayim yagid davar,
no, the birds will carry our words. I don't care, what do
you mean just us? Nevertheless, I don't care. I don't want to
do any, you know, I'm afraid to do anything, the word will
get out. אמר ליה, amar leh, אנא הוא, ana hu, I am
he, I am Herod. אי הוה ידענא דזהירי רבנן כולי האי, i
hava yadana de'zehirei rabanan kulei hai, if I knew the Rabbis were
so careful to, you know, not sort of, you know, undermine the
king and so on, and to be careful with how they speak,
לא הוה קטילנא להו, lo hava katilina lehu, I wouldn't have killed
them all out.
Now it's interesting because at
the end of the day, he wasn't swearing loyalty to Herod, you
know, he was actually just saying like it's incautious, it's to go
ahead and to say this. I mean, the first response actually was
saying like we have to be respectful, even if we don't like
who he is, and even if we think he sort of seized
the power illegitimately or whatever, you know, we still have to go
ahead and have respect for the position. You know, the next stage,
it was sort of like, it was sort of like I just,
I'm just afraid about that the word will get out. So it's
a, it's a sort of self-preservation caution, you know, caution, it's not
because of respect for the position. But the point still being nevertheless,
if I would have known that I could have kept the Rabbis
alive and whatever would have motivated them, they still would have sort
of been, you know, careful with their words, respectful, whatever the motivation
would have been, they would have acted in a way of respect
and I wouldn't have wiped them out. Okay, so he felt bad
now that he had wiped out all the Rabbis. They tolerated, they
tolerated wicked behavior on the part of the leader. Yeah, right, okay
in your sugya. Yes, that is true. Okay, so the Gemara says,
השתא מאי תקנתיה דהוא גברא, hashta mai takantei de'hu gavra, so what
now is the, so now he said, now I feel really guilty,
what can I do to make it up? אמר ליה, amar leh,
so now Bava ben Buta said to him, הוא כיבה אורו של
עולם, hu kiva oro shel olam, he, meaning you, destroyed the light
of the world, דכתיב כי נר מצוה ותורה אור, de'khitiv ki ner
mitzvah ve'torah or, you destroyed the Rabbis that are the source of
light in the world. ילך ויעסוק באורו של עולם, yelech ve'ye'asok be'oro
shel olam, now you should go and you should involve yourself in
spreading light,
דכתיב ונהרו אליו כל הגוים, de'khitiv ve'naharu elav kol hagoyim, the Beit
HaMikdash, all of the nations will sort of be drawn to it.
So the word like venaharu is also like echoes the word ner
and or and so on. סגי נהור. sagi nahar. Right. That's true
also. In Aramaic the word naharu is or. Okay. איכא דאמרי הכי
אמר ליה, ika de'amri hachi amar leh, or some say he said
the following, הוא סימא עינו של עולם, hu suma eino shel olam,
you destroyed the eye of the world. Again also notice that he
also destroyed his light and his and right, so he's destroyed, talking
about destroying the Rabbis as cutting off the light and the eye,
but also that's very true about him personally. So he, meaning you,
Herod, destroyed the light and the eye of the world, דכתיב היה
מעיני העדה, de'khitiv haya me'einei ha'edah, from the eyes of the community,
which means the eyes of the Sanhedrin is the way the Rabbis
read it, you know, a sin is done. ילך ויתעסק בעינו של
עולם, yelech v'yitasek be'eino shel olam, you should now go and try
to restore the eye, the center of the world, דכתיב הנני מחלל
את מקדשי, de'khitiv hineni mechalel et mikdashi, behold I will destroy my
sanctuary, גאון עוזכם מחמד עיניכם, ge'on uzchem machmad eineichem, the glory of
your strength, the desire of your eyes. The desirous thing of your
eyes. Okay, so again there’s an obvious point here about eyes and
light and he’s been blinded, but he’s also using this to describe
to the effect of destroying the rabbis and now you can replace
it, try to replace it with the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Okay,
but again it’s interesting within the context of the story that the
primary sort of source of light, of like these central religious force
is the rabbis, and the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash is a substitute
for the rabbis. So you have to like appreciate a little bit
the historical irony of that, right, because historically the בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash was the center and then that was replaced by Rabbinic Judaism
and here it's sort of reversing it. Oh, the rabbis were the
center, you destroyed the rabbis, well maybe what we can do is
we can make a substitute and really work on making a nice
בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash.
Okay, so okay. אמלי מסתפינא ממלכותא. Amlei nistafina mimachusa. Now this is
very interesting. This gets back, you know, before it echoes before that
he would say I’m not going to say anything because they’ll hear
about it, right, and that’s why he was, you know, בבא Bava
wasn’t sort of cursing him. So now Herod is saying I’m afraid
of the Roman government. I can’t act that way without permission from
the Roman government. Ultimately we’re subject to the Roman government. מסתפינא ממלכותא.
Mistafina mimachusa. אמרי, Amrei, here’s how you can handle it. שדר שליחא,
Shadar shlicha, send a messenger, וליזל שתא, v’leizel shata, let him take
a year getting to them, וליעכב שתא, v’leakev
shata, let him spend a year there waiting for an audience with
I guess the Caesar or whatever it is and to get permission,
וליהדר שתא,
v’leihadar shata, and let him take a year to get his way
find his way back. So let him take three years till you
get the message back. They didn’t have email those days.
אדי הכי והכי, Adei hachi v’hachi, by
the time the messenger finally gets back, סתרתיה ליה ובניתיה ליה, sastis
lei v’banistas lei, that'll
give you enough time to
knock it down and to rebuild it. So you get permission for
something you’ve done after you’ve done it. Right. So there’s actually a
principle like this in business, I remember reading this somewhere, which is
basically called unless otherwise advised. Like how do you deal with a
supervisor that never gives you an answer to a question? So you
basically send them an email and you say here’s what I’m going
to do unless you would tell me unless I hear from you
otherwise. And then you go and then you don’t hear from them
you go ahead and do what you wanted to do. Okay but
anyway so here he’s going to but it’s so it’s similar I’m
going to do it I’m going to by the time I get
the answer it’ll be too late to do anything about it. Okay
so anyway. So this corroborates this. Right. Some historians I think say
that this is a in other words he didn’t wait around he
just... Okay that might have been that he didn’t wait around that’s
interesting I didn’t know historically what the record shows but it certainly
took much more than three years. No, no, right I mean right
exactly he didn’t wait for an answer. He went out and he
just started it on his own. Right, construction company. Right. I mean
I think I know that historians think that it might have taken
like like tens of years, you know, 40 years maybe whatever a
real lot of time. By the way in terms of the historical
background about all of this what I should say is if you
look at the last רש"י Rashi on ג' עמוד ב', gimmel amud
bais, רש"י Rashi says למפרע היכי אספריה עצה להורדוס l’mifra heichi asprei
eitza l’hordus about this בבא בן בוטא Bava ben Buta כדאמרינן בלקמן
בשמעתין k’d’amrinan b’likaman b’shmatin וכתובה היא ביוסיפון בן גוריון. v’khsuva hi b’Yosifon
ben Goryon. Now יוסיפון בן גוריון Yosifon ben Goryon is not Josephus.
יוסיפון בן גוריון Yosifon ben Goryon is a is a is a
middle age again medieval thank you my my phone these days. I
don’t know. Anyway I’m just going to turn it off. Is a
medieval work which was actually presented itself as a Hebrew translation of
the Greek Josephus but it was not it was essentially a forgery.
Okay and that’s why יוסיפון בן גוריון Yosifon ben Goryon which is
what a lot of ראשונים Rishonim quote have a lot of parallels
to the גמרא's Gemara sort of stories but are not actually in
Josephus. Okay but anyway but that was a pseudo-Josephus this יוסיפון בן
גוריון. Yosifon ben Goryon. All right but anyway but anyway but this
is the basic point here is that he went down and he
started it without having yet received advice okay act first you know
it’s easier to get what is it it’s easier to get forgiveness
than permission. Okay so anyway so he went ahead and then you’ll
get your answer later. ואדי הכי והכי v’adei hachi v’hachi where were
we. Okay ואדי הכי והכי סתרתיה ליה ובניתיה ליה v’adei hachi v’hachi
sastis lei v’banistas lei you'll knock it down and you'll rebuild. עבדא
הכי Avad hachi he did that. שלחו ליה Shelachoo lei then by
the time so here was the response he got back. אם לא
סתרת Im lo satarta if you haven’t knocked down the בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash yet אל תסתור al tistur don’t do it. This is
from the Roman government. ואם סתרת v’im satarta if you knocked it
down אל תבני al tivni don’t build. ואם סתרת ובנית v’im satarta
oovanita and if you knocked it down and rebuilt עבדא בישא avda
bisha a bad slave bad servant בתר דעבדין ממלכין batar d’avdin mis’malkhin
after they go ahead and do what they want then they ask
permission. Okay אם זיינך עלך im zayanakh alakh if you have your
if you have your your weapons on you you think you’re now
you’re
walking around with strutting around
with all your authority you know and you’ve got your sword on
you and all of that. ספרך כאן Siphrakha kan we got your
records back here in Rome. We know that you’re really a slave.
You know you’re now going around acting like king you think you’re
a big shot. Yeah this is now we see that you know
you’re really just like you know what type you’re really like a
lowly servant who acts in this. rebellious way. We got your records
back here. לא רכא ולא בר רכא *lo racha v'lo bar racha*,
not a king and not the son of a king. הורדוס עבדא
קלניא מתעביד *Hordis avda kalnya mit'avid*, הורדוס *Hordis* the slave made himself
into a free man. You are not really a free man. So
Gemara says קלניא *kalnya* apparently means a free man. I don't know,
I'm sure somebody will tell me based on... yeah, it's probably exactly.
So מאי רכא *mai racha*? Now what does the word רכא *racha*
mean? Since they already knew the word קלניא *kalnya* meant a free
man, but what does the word רכא *racha* mean? מלכותא *malchuta*, a
king, דכתיב אנכי היום רך ומשוח מלך *dichtiv anochi hayom racha umashuach
melech*. I today am young and have been anointed king. So, Rex!
Oh, Rex! Oh, that's good. שקויעח *shkoach*. Okay. ואיבעית אימא ve'iba'it eima
מהכא ויקראו לפניו אברך *v'iba'it eima mehacha v'yakre'u lefanav avrech*. That's by
Yosef. That's at least somewhat better because the other word רך *rach*,
although it was in the context of king, meant a young person.
Anyway, אמרי *amri*. Now, okay, so that's how הורדוס *Hordis* seized the
throne, tried to gain legitimacy of the throne, according to this story
wiped out the Rabbis, left a Rabbi, then realized his mistake, respected
the Rabbis, rabbinic authority, whatever, and then to make up for wiping
up the Rabbis, rebuilt the בית המקדש beit hamikdash *Beis Hamikdash*. And
then also did it in a way of rebelling against his Roman
overlords. So once again acting as this sort of rebellious slave. Now,
now we get to the actual building of the בית המקדש beit
hamikdash *Beis Hamikdash*. אמרי *amri*, they say, מי שלא ראה בנין הורדוס
*mi shelo ra binyan Hordis*, whoever did not see the construction of
הורדוס *Hordis*, the second בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*, לא ראה בנין נאה
מימיו *lo ra binyan na'eh miyamav*. He's never seen a beautiful construction
building in their lives. Okay, this was the most beautiful edifice you
could have imagined. במאי בנייה *b'mai banya*? With what did he build
it? אמר רבה באבני שישא ומרמרא *amar raba b'avnei shaisha u'marmara* with
basically the way רש״י *Rashi* says it's a type of like a
green and white marble. איכא דאמרי *ika d'amri* some say באבני כוחלא
שישא ומרמרא *b'avnei kuchla shaisha u'marmara*, no, blue and white marble. Blue
and white. Yeah, exactly, there you go. Colors of... yeah, he was
anticipating the colors of מדינת ישראל *Medinat Yisrael*. אפיק שפתא ועייל שפתא
*apheik sapha v'ayeil sapha*, so like the lips went in and out.
So it was like, it wasn't like a flat facade but it
was, you know, zigzag... well, every presumably I assume what it means
is that every other row, the odd rows protruded and the even
rows receded or something like that. כי היכי דנקבלה סידא *ki heichi
d'nikabel saida* in order that it should be like a basis for
putting on the plaster or something. I don't exactly understand that.
Plaster all over this nice marble?
Well, I guess it means like between the rows, not on the
face
of it, but no, bit of an illustration here suggesting some of
the... yes, stones. All right.
Yeah, so I mean basic, all right, like whatever you mean it
was sort of like this.
On one side it actually is a straight line but on the
other side the cement or whatever it is...
yeah, although I don't really understand it. What? So it was sort
of like this? Oh no, actually I didn't do that
right. Anyway, whatever it
would be.
But we do know that Herodian stones also have are embossed. Aha.
So I guess apparently the inner ones
were a little receded and that they would put plaster here or
something like that.
Yes, correct, they were receded a little bit, even at the face
of
it, each stone on
top of the next one receded a little bit for stability. Oh
really? Also the outside facade, you know that embossed framing, that's Herodian.
Well, that I know, but that's... I'm not sure that's what they
mean here. All right.
So something like that. סבר למשעייה בדהבא *savar l'mishayei b'dahava*.
They wanted to
smooth over the front of it with gold, like make it all
gold-plated, okay? אמרו ליה רבנן *amru lei rabanan*, so the Rabbis said,
שבקיה *shavkei*, no, leave it the way it is without the gold
plating. דהכי שפיר טפי *d'hachi shapir tvei*, it looks nicer this way.
דמיחזי כי אוותא דימא *d'mechzei ki avata d'yama*, it looks like the
waves of the sea. If it's blue and white and it's going
in and out, it looks nice, it looks like the waves of
the sea. בבא בן בוטא *Baba Ben Buta* now, okay, so that's
the building of the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*. ובבא בן בוטא היכי
עביד הכי *u'Baba Ben Buta heichi avid hachi*, how did he do
this? how did he become complicit in the, you know, with the
evil king Herod, even though it was for a good purpose? והא
אמר רבא בר רב יהודה אמר רב ואי תימא רבי יהושע בן
לוי מפני מה נענש דניאל *v'ha amar Rava bar Rav Yehuda amar
Rav v'itayma Rabi Yehoshua ben Levi mipnei ma ne'enash Daniel*? Why was
Daniel punished? מפני שהשיא עצה לנבוכדנצר *mipnei she'hisi eitza l'Nevuchadnezzar*. Because he
gave advice to Nebuchadnezzar, even good advice, advice that was for to
help other people. שנאמר *shene'emar*, as it says, because you know Nebuchadnezzar
has this very disturbing dream and he goes tells it to Daniel,
and Daniel says back to him, להן מלכא מלכי ישפר עלך וחטאך
בצדקה פרוק *lehein malka malchi yishpar alach v'chatayach b'tzidka perok*, therefore the
king, my advice should find favor in your eyes, your sin you
should redeem with charity. My advice, I think, means should find favor
in your eyes, and you should go ahead and redeem your sin
with charity, ועויתך במיחן ענין *v'avayasach b'mikan anayin*, and your iniquity with
being kind to the poor. So you have, you know, whatever this
vision dream you've had that bad things are going to come. so
the way you can forestall it or prevent it is by doing
all of these righteous deeds. Okay. הן תהוי ארכא לשלוותך that way
there will be a lengthening of your tranquility of the good times.
וכתיב ukhtiv and it says כלא מטא על נבוכדנצר מלכא kula meta
al nevukhadnetzar malka all of these things occurred since Nevukhadnetzar all the
visions of the dream. וכתיב ukhtiv ולקצת ירחין תרי עשר uliktzat yarkhin
terei asar after twelve months. So there was a twelve month reprieve
of the vision because he did he followed Daniel's advice. All right.
So that doesn't say that Daniel did anything wrong by giving him
that advice. איבעית אימא iba'it eima but we'll see how we know
Daniel did something wrong in a minute. But anyway so you're not
supposed to give kings advice even if it's going to help other
people. You don't want to I guess be complicit with evil kings.
So the גמרא gemara says איבעית אימא iba'it eima שאני עבדא דחייב
במצוות. shani avda dechayev bemitzvot. Okay. Number one is that it's different
because as a slave he is Herod as a slave, Herod as
a slave is חייב במצוות. chayev bemitzvot. So therefore we should actually
take an interest in Herod's acting properly and doing the right thing
even if he is an evil king because at the end of
the day he's also חייב במצוות chayev bemitzvot and we should care
about his religious well-being, which again is funny because I would much
more care about the populace than I would care about the king.
So what do I care if it's an evil king if I'm
helping a king who's not חייב במצוות chayev bemitzvot to do מצוות
mitzvot or I'm helping a king who is חייב במצוות chayev bemitzvot
to do מצוות? mitzvot? What I should care about is am I
helping everybody else for all of his subjects? So I really don't
understand why that should determine whether or not you should give helpful
advice to a king. ואיבעית אימא if you want, שאני בית המקדש
דאי לא מלכותא לא מיבני. shani beit hamikdash de'i la malkhuta la
mivni. No, no, no, which is at least a more understandable answer.
Here the result of building a בית המקדש is something you can't
do without being involved and complicit in this king's government. So this
warrants this type of participation whereas other things would not warrant it.
Okay. That at least makes sense. Okay. ודניאל מנלן דאיענש vedaniel minalan
de'iansh and where do we know Daniel was punished? אילימא משום דכתיב
eileima mishum dekhtiv ותקרא אסתר להתך, vatikra ester lehatach, Esther called Hatach.
ואמר רב ve'amar rav התך זה דניאל, hatach zeh daniel, Hatach is
Daniel. הניחא haniha so therefore and therefore why does that show that
he got punished? הניחא למאן דאמר שחתכוהו מגדולתו. haniha leman de'amar shehatkhuhu
migedulato. So if the word Hatach indicates like cut,, that he no
longer has his status. Here he is some messenger boy for Esther.
So then you see that he was punished. אלא למאן דאמר שכל
דברי מלכות נחתכין על פיו, ela leman de'amar shekol divrei malkhut nehtakhin
al piv, but if the word Hatach means that he actually still
had this power that he was the one that all the edicts
were ultimately sealed by him, so מאי איכא למימר mai ika lemeimar
where do you see that he was punished? דשדיוהו לגובא דאריוותא. deshadyuhu
leguva de'aryavata. Okay because he was thrown into the pit of lions.
So that was how he was punished. Alright, in the end he
was saved from that. But anyway it's a quite fascinating גמרא gemara
because really what's so bad about giving helpful advice to kings even
if it's going to help other people, telling Nevukhadnetzar to give צדקה
tzedakah and telling, so is it that just being close to a
wicked government makes you complicit even though the role that you're playing
is only a positive role? Like it's not exactly clear why the
גמרא gemara thinks that this is such a bad thing. It's also
not clear why it thinks that the fact that Herod is חייב
במצוות chayev bemitzvot makes it different. Yes. And this whole סוגיא sugya
in part to me is about the ambivalence of how to respond
to such a power. It's dangerous but there's an ethical imperative. But
there maybe there's exceptions. But it's dangerous. And that's it seems to
me holding on to all those tensions. Yeah. Yeah, I agree with
that. Yeah. So briefly was Herod an עבד כנעני? eved kena'ani? He
was an Idumean convert. His family was forcibly converted by the חשמונאים
chashmonaim that went through the Negev and southern areas and forcibly converted
and circumcised the Idumean people. And he was enslaved by them? He
was that I don't know but he was, yes, I mean the
חשמונאים chashmonaim used the Idumeans, they were like second class citizens. That's
what I got from Josephus. There you go. Alright. יישר כח. yashar
koach. Alright. Okay. Back to now the גמרא. gemara. That was a
fascinating little digression about the building of the בית המקדש and seeing
it as a type of almost a בית כנסת, beit knesset, at
least for part of that discussion. Now back to the גמרא. gemara.
הכל כמנהג המדינה hakol keminhag hamedina what? Herod decided to cause wars
and rebellion and things like that like this Helen of Troy you
saw this one woman the whole... Oh you mean the whole thing
about the face that the face that launched a thousand ships right
the whole linking here about lust and power the relationship about lust
and power right okay very good alright moving moving forward הכל כמנהג
המדינה hakol keminhag hamedina הכל לאתויי מאי hakol le'atuyei mai now this
is the משנה mishna that says once you agree to build the
wall the parameters of the wall are based on what the norms
of the society are. So what is that coming to include? לאתויי
אתרא דנהיגי בהוצא ודפנא le'atuyei atra denehigi behutza vedafna even if it's
not with these nice types of stones and bricks even if it's
just with basically branches a type of a wood wall. Even that
is considered legitimate enough to, you know, nobody, you can't say it's
not a real wall, obviously we meant something more than that. If
that's the custom, then that is implicit what you've agreed upon. Okay,
הסיפא, hasifa, if נפלה הכותל nafla hakotel המקום והאבנים של שניהם, hamakom
veha'avanim shel shneihem, if the wall falls because the presumption without any
other evidence is that these walls are built based on both of
their contributions and both of their properties, so if a wall falls
and it's been around for 100 years and we don't know whose
it was, the presumption is that it equally belongs to both, you
know, both people, and it's and the property equally belongs to both
people. So the Gemara says פשיטא pshita obviously, no לא צריכא דנפל
לרשותא דחד מינייהו, lo tzricha denafal lerushuta dechad mineihu, it all fell
into one person's domain. אי נמי דפנינהו חד לרשותא דידיה, i nami
defaninhu chad lerushuta didei, or one person, you know, moved it all
into his domain, you know, מהו דתימא אימר איהו סתרי והוי אידך
המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה, mahu detaima eimar ihu satrei vehavi idach hamotzi
mechaveiro alav haraya, maybe we should treat it as a ספק. safek.
We don't know exactly. The other guy is in control. קא משמע
לן ka mashma lan that we don't treat it as a ספק
safek since the standard is that it's always built by the contribution
of both, we treat it as if we definitely know that it's
both unless there's evidence to prove otherwise. וכן בגינה מקום שנהגו לגדור
מחייבין אותו, vechein begina makom shenahagu ligdor mechayvin oto, similarly in a
garden in a place where the practice is to make a wall,
you obligate them to make a wall, okay, even if they don't
agree to make a wall. So the question is that's an obvious
hard line to parse because what is it saying, what is the
norm of a garden? הגופא קשיא, hagufa kashya, מר תנא וכן בגינה
מקום שנהגו לגדור מחייבין אותו, mar tana vechein begina makom shenahagu ligdor
mechayvin oto, the simple way to read this mishna is in a
garden, if it is a place where they normally make a wall,
you obligate הא סתמא ha stama which means that without that the
norm would be אין מחייבין אותו, ein mechayvin oto, it's not assumed
to be a place you make a wall and you wouldn't obligate.
So okay, הא סתמא אין מחייבין אותו, ha stama ein mechayvin oto,
אימא סיפא, eima seifa, let's look at the end of the mishna.
אבל בבקעה, aval bebika, but if it's in a valley in a
wheat field, מקום שנהגו שלא לגדור אין מחייבין אותו, makom shenahagu shelo
ligdor ein mechayvin oto, if it's a place that you don't have
the practice, you don't obligate הא סתמא, ha stama, the implication is
מחייבין אותו mechayvin oto that you do obligate, meaning the way the
mishna is written, it sounds like a garden the default is to
not require a wall and a valley the default is to require
a wall. So the Gemara says that doesn't make any sense, השתא
סתם גינה אמרת לא, hashta stam gina amart lo, if a garden,
you assume that the default is not to require a wall, בקעה
מיבעיא, bika mibaya, would you think that a valley would be any
different, there's much less of a need for a wall in a
valley than in a garden? So אמר אביי הכי קאמר, amar Abaye
hachi ka'amar, here's how you have to read the mishna: וכן סתם
גינה, vechein stam gina, a normal garden is an obligation to build
a wall, ובמקום שנהגו לגדור בבקעה, uvmakom shenahagu ligdor bebika, and also
if it's in a valley and there's a practice to build a
wall, you also obligate מחייבין אותו. mechayvin oto. You treated two cases
into that one. אמר ליה רבא, amar lei Rava, Rava said, no,
אם כן מאי אבל, im kein mai aval, so if it's already
said that it's a valley, it's in a place to, it's you
know, if there is a norm to build a wall, you obligate,
then why does the end of the mishna say, but in a
valley, you don't obligate, meaning we've already just, you know, the norm
is we don't, I mean you've already addressed the valley case, what
do you mean what's the word of the "but"? אלא אמר רבא,
ela amar Rava, so Rava says הכי קתני, hachi katani, and this
is how we read it earlier, וכן סתם גינה, vechein stam gina,
a normal garden כמקום שנהגו לגדור דמי, kemakom shenahagu ligdor dami, a
normal garden is presumed to be a place where the practice is
to make a fence, it's not a normal garden if the practice
is to make a wall, a normal garden is a place where
the practice can be assumed to be to make a wall and
therefore in a normal garden you have to make a wall ומחייבין
אותו, umechayvin oto, אבל סתם בקעה, aval stam bika, a normal valley,
not if there isn't a practice to make a wall, no, a
normal valley is a place where there isn't a practice to make
a wall. אבל סתם בקעה כמקום שלא נהגו דמי ואין מחייבין אותו,
aval stam bika kemakom shelo nahagu dami ve'ein mechayvin oto, you don't
obligate. Okay, so does everybody get it right? Because the mishna said
basically וכן בגינה vechein begina מקום שנהגו לגדור, makom shenahagu ligdor, okay,
instead אבל בבקעה aval bebika מקום שנהגו, makom shenahagu, you know, שלא
לגדור shelo ligdor etc. So rather than reading this a garden if
it is a place שנהגו לגדור shenahagu ligdor and a בקעה bika
if it's a place שלא נהגו, shelo nahagu, we take out the
word "if". A standard garden is a place that נהגו לגדור nahagu
ligdor and you have to build a wall, but a בקעה bika
is a place that's נהגו שלא לגדור nahagu shelo ligdor and you
don't obligate, so we just read it as an "is" rather than
as an "if". I just for the sake of time, just hold
the questions, we're just moving on. Okay, אלא אם רוצה כונס לתוך
שלו בונה ועושה חזית. ela im rotze kones letoch shelo bone ve'ose
hazit. Okay, so fine, so now we got the idea based we
had the whole earlier discussion whether when you agree to build a
wall you have to build it or because even if you don't
agree once you split you have to build it because of because
of the issue of היזק ראיה, hezek re'iya, but one way or
another way now you're building a wall and now it says like
this, but if it's a case where you weren't obligated to build
a wall, it wasn't היזק ראיה, hezek re'iya, we didn't agree, I
couldn't convince you to agree to build a wall, I'm going to
build it all in my property. So because there's a presumption that
any wall is both of our, of our, you know, materials and
both of our properties and now I was forced to build it
all on my property with my money, how am I going to
signal? That, so that it will be remembered, you know, a hundred
years from now when the wall falls, it will be remembered that
it's mine and not yours, and that it's my property and my
yard and my building materials. So what does the משנה Mishna. *Mishna*
say? רצה כונס לתוך שלו בונה את החזית *Ratza kones letoch shelo
boneh et hachazit*. What I do is I make some type of
a facing on the wall, some type of a thing that, you
know, that signals that this wall was all built on my property
and from and from my material. Building on mine, yeah. So, so
what is this חזית *chazit*? How do I do this? מאי חזית
*Mai chazit*? What is this חזית *chazit*? אמר רב הונא כופיא לקרנא
לבר *Amar Rav Huna kofya lekarna levar*. You basically turn the corner
on the outside. So I guess if you imagine, I don't know,
whatever, if you imagine right, how am I going to draw this?
Imagine. I don't know, if this is, if this is ראובן Reuven
*Reuven*, right, and here's שמעון Shimon *Shimon*, and here's the wall, so
rather than sort of making this just straight, you know, you maybe
turn the edge of the wall out like that. Okay. So that,
so that shows this that ראובן Reuven *Reuven*, it's all ראובן'ס *Reuven's*
because the edge of the wall is turned out. It's not a
flat corner. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this, ונעביד
מלגאו *venavid miligav*? How about turning the corner on the inside? No,
עביד חבריה נמי מלבר ואמר דידי ודידיה הוא *avid chavreih nami milivar
ve'amar didi vedideih hu*. No, because if it's turned on the inside,
if you were to turn this into you to show it's yours,
then שמעון Shimon *Shimon* would just make an addition on the wall
and turn it into him and say it's equally his. He could
just file it away. אי הכי השתא נמי גייז ליה חבריה ואמר
דידי ודידיה הוא *I hachi hashta nami gayiz leih chavreih ve'amar didi
vedideih hu*. So here too, he'll just cut off the corner. So
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says no, גזוזייא מידע ידיע *gezuyei meida yedia*. You
can see that it's been cut off. So that, you know, what's
he going to do? Plaster? You'll see he plastered on top of
it. So that'll be visible. איכא דאמרי *Ika d'amri*, some say the
reverse. אמר רב הונא מכפי לקרנא מלגאו *Amar Rav Huna machfei lekarna
miligav*. No, you turn the corner on the inside. Exactly what we
the opposite. ונעביד מלבר *Vena'avid milivar*? Turn it on the outside. גייז
ליה חבריה ואמר דידי ודידיה הוא *Gayiz leih chavreih ve'amar didi vedideih
hu*. So הכי, אי הכי השתא נמי לייפי ליה חבריה ואמר דידי
ודידיה הוא *hachi, i hachi hashta nami laifay leih chavreih ve'amar didi
vedideih hu*. So if you turn it on the inside, so שמעון
Shimon *Shimon* now will turn his side on the inside and say
it's his. No, ליפופא מידע ידיע *lifufa meida yedia*. He would have
to make an addition after the wall was built in order to
turn the corner on the inside and you'll be able to see
that it's an addition. So therefore, you know, that will, so one
way or the other, either you'll see the addition or you see
the cutting off and you'll protect yourself. הגמרא *Hagemara* says והא אנן
תנן חזית מלבר *veha anan tenan chazit milivar*. But one minute, it
says you put the סימן siman *siman* on the outside. Okay, we
read, you're reading it, you're putting it on the inside of the
wall. So גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says קשיא *kashya*. Alright, that's טאקע *takeh*
a problem. Alright, anyway רבי יוחנן אמר *Rabbi Yochanan amar*. Anyway, so
you do some type of a thing. So רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*
says משייע באמה מלבר *meshayaya be'amah milivar*. Basically you plaster over, right
here again on שמעון'ס *Shimon's* side, you put a layer, an extra
layer of plaster. And that shows that it's his. That that's ראובן'ס
*Reuven's* wall. So גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says ונעביד מלגאו *venavid miligav*? Why
not put a layer of plaster on your side? No, עביד חבריה
נמי מלבר ואמר דידי ודידיה הוא *avid chavreih nami milivar ve'amar didi
vedideih hu*. Then שמעון Shimon, *Shimon* will put a plaster layer of
plaster on his side. So גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says אי הכי השתא
נמי דקליף ליה חבריה ואמר דידי ודידיה הוא *i hachi hashta nami
dekalif leih chavreih ve'amar didi vedideih hu*. So if you put a
layer of plaster on שמעון'ס *Shimon's* side, שמעון Shimon *Shimon* will just
remove the layer of plaster. So גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says no, קליפא
מידע ידיע *kelifa meida yedia*. You'll be able to see that the
plaster's been removed. I don't know, to me, that's a harder argument,
especially over the passage of time that you can see plaster's been
removed. I don't know. Anyway, הוצא *hutza*. Now what if it's a
wall that's made out of sticks, out of leaves, or whatever, out
of branches? How are you going to make a סימן siman *siman*
on a wall out of branches in terms of whose wall it
is that's going to last? So אמר רב נחמן כניפי וארכי מלבר
*Amar Rav Nachman kenifay v'archei milivar*. You basically bend the branches, similar
to the way here you built the wall with a corner pointing
out, you bend the branches to the outside and the pointy part
of the branches are pointing on the outside and the fact that
they're all pointing in that direction that shows that it belongs to
you, to the guy where at the side it's not pointing on.
So גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says ונעביד מלגאו *venavid miligav*? Point it on
the inside. עביד חבריה נמי מלבר ואמר דידי ודידיה הוא *Avid chavreih
nami milivar ve'amar didi vedideih hu*. Okay, somehow the guy will also
manage to, I don't know, point the things on his side if
you do that. אי הכי השתא נמי גייז ושדי ליה ואמר דידי
ודידיה הוא *I hachi hashta nami gayiz veshadi leih ve'amar didi vedideih
hu*. So here too he'll just cut off the points of the
branches and he'll throw it out and he'll say it's mine too.
So גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says fine, משקיל טינא *meshkil tina*. Fine, so
similar to what we said before, you plaster over one side and
presumably then the remnants will be, yeah, on the outside of the
branches. I don't know how to, what to say. Anyway, and therefore
if he tries to remove it, presumably it'll be visible. So גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says השתא נמי אתי חבריה וקליף ליה *hashta nami ati
chavreih vekalif leih*. So oh, what do you mean, he'll just remove
the plaster? No, קליפא מידע ידיע *kelifa meida yedia*. That'll be noticeable.
אמר אביי Abaye *Amar Abaye*. אביי Abaye, *Abaye* says הוצא לית ליה
תקנתא takanta *hutza leit leih takanta*. No, a wall out of branches
or wood, there's no way to make a good permanent סימן siman
*siman* on it. אלא בשטרא *Ela beshtara*. So in that case you
actually get need to get some documentation. Okay. So get, you have
a שטר shtar. *shtar* that says that it's all yours, that the
other guy signed, and you go ahead put it in your safety
deposit box. Okay. אבל אם עשו מדעת שניהם *Aval im asu mida'at
sheneihem*. Now if they both made it and it was a place
that normally you wouldn't make a wall, like it's in a valley,
but we've agreed to make a wall, it says you make a
סימן siman. *siman* on both sides. So גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*'s going to
say why a סימן siman *siman* on both sides? How about just
having no סימן siman, *siman*? So let's take a look. אמר ליה
Amar lei: רב פפא מפרזיקא Rav Papa mi-Prazika לרב אשי, so רב
פפא מפרזיקא says to רב אשי: Rav Ashi: לא יעשו לא לזה
ולא לזה, lo ya'asu lo le-zeh ve-lo le-zeh, how about not making
a סימן siman on either side in this case? אמר ליה: Amar
lei, No, צריכא דקדים חד מנייהו ועביד דידיה. tzericha de-kadim chad mi-naihu
ve-avid didai. No, no, the case is you're right, we could start
with no סימנים. simanim. But then if one guy went and he
did something on his side to try to indicate make it look
like it was his, then you have to go and do something
on your side. Okay, ואי לא עביד חבריה אמר דידי הוא. ve-i
lo avid chavre amar didai hu. And if you don't do something
as well, he'll claim it's all his. So the גמרא Gemara says:
ותני תקנתא לרמאי? Ve-tani takanta le-ramai? And we're going to teach something,
a תקנתא takanta. how to deal with like, you know, with deceitful
people, deceitful people like, you know, what's the rabbis' business trying, like
which is funny, you're not assisting deceitful people, you're counteracting them. But
the גמרא Gemara. maybe says, maybe we should just why are we
assuming that people are acting incorrectly? I don't really fully understand the
question, but okay. אמר ליה, Amar lei, the גמרא Gemara says back,
בשלמא, bishlama, no, רישא, reisha, I'm going to say it like... קא
משמע לן, kama shema lan, so ותני תקנתא לרמאי? tani takanta le-ramai?
קא משמע לן? Kama shema lan? No, that's the question. And is
the תנא Tanna coming to teach us how to deal with רמאי?
ramai? אמר ליה, Amar lei, ורישא לאו תקנתא לרמאי הוא? ve-reisha lav
takanta le-ramai hu? I don't understand. The first part where it talks
about a סימן on one side is also telling you how to
prevent people from making false claims. So the גמרא Gemara says no.
אמר ליה, no, that doesn't bother me. בשלמא רישא תנא דינא. Bishlama
reisha tana dina. The רישא reisha was primarily there to teach me
the הלכה, halacha, which is that you can't in a valley, you
can't force the other guy to make it. And if you're going
to make it, you have to make it all on your side.
And once it's telling you that basic הלכה halacha that you're going
to have to make it all on your side, it's going to
tell you and here's how you'll do it in a way to
prevent false claims. Okay, ומשום דדינא תני תקנתא, u-mishum de-dina tana takanta,
because of the דין din then it's telling you the תקנתא. אלא
סיפא דינא קתני? Ela seifa dina katani? דקתני תקנתא? De-katani takanta? In
the סיפא seifa saying, oh, but if you both agreed, so that's
not a הלכה. halacha. Of course I know if we both agreed
we can build it in the middle. So the whole purpose of
the סיפא seifa is to tell me how to protect myself in
a case of a joint wall. So the גמרא says that's funny
that the תנא Tanna puts it as his responsibility to give people
advice to how to protect themselves against cheats. Okay. So the גמרא
says, again, I don't understand why not, like, you know, why aren't
we trying to help people in all these areas of דיני ממונות?
dinei mamonot? But anyway, maybe it's just saying it's not a legal
point, it's just sort of, you know, a question about just taking
necessary precautions. Anyway, so why do you bother telling me the end
case for the whole purpose of telling me how to protect yourself?
אמר רבינא הכא בהוצי עסקינן. Amar Ravina hacha be-huzia askinan. Okay, so
here's why we said the end case. Because we're talking about a
case of this like, you know, wall made out of branches. And
we're telling you that you make these סימנים, simanim, this extra case,
it really is extra, we didn't have to say it, and it's
not our business to tell you how to protect yourself, that we
wouldn't primarily say something about that. But we said this extra case
to indicate there are other cases that require that you can do
a סימן where you might not have normally thought you could do
a סימן. Which is that case? A wood wall, a branch wall.
הכא בהוצי עסקינן לאפוקי מדאביי. Hacha be-huzia askinan le-afukei mi-de-Abaye. And it's
coming to reject אביי's position. דאמר אביי הוצי לית ליה תקנתא אלא
בשטר. De-amar Abaye huzia leit lei takanta ela be-shtar. That if you
have this branch wall you need a שטר. קא משמע לן דבחזי
סגיא. Kama shema lan de-be-chazi sagia. So it has this extra case
of talking about a חזי chazi on each side, not to tell
you the עיקר ikkar idea of how to protect yourself, that you
don't need the תנא Tanna to advise me about. But it's coming
to tell you that there's extra another case of a wall in
which you can use a סימן where you might have thought you
couldn't use a סימן, this case of a branch wall, not like
אביי, we believe that a סימן will be effective here as well.
But how in the world does that teach you that? It doesn't.
Just from the very fact that it's extra. It's one of those
cases. Since it's extra, it must be coming to teach us something.
It must be coming up with a million things. I understand. That's
the rabbis' general approach, you know, that, you know, that it's sort
of like the similar way they דרשן darshen פסוקים. pesukim. I'm serious
about this. They can sometimes דרשן darshen a משנה. Mishna. Oh, you
have this extra וו, vav, that's coming to teach me something I
was thinking about anyway, that there's no logical deductive way I could
get it out of the פסוק pasuk but you know, right, what's
the law? If it's extra, so you go back to, you go
backwards. Why, why didn't he just say that you actually need it
because didn't we say that if you actually state that you're going
to build a wall, yeah, then even after, if you change your
mind afterwards, you still have to build it? No, that was a
discussion in the גמרא, not in the משנה. Mishnah And actually the
גמרא there said you don't have to. Oh, I'm sorry, that was
about splitting. By the building of the wall, that if you did
a קניין kinyan then you do become obligated. Right. So you're just
saying there could have been something else that this was telling us.
I agree. You know, the גמרא has its own, it chooses to
read in to extra pieces the things that it's sort of assuming
anyway. All right. Now we move on, so that was a very
nice, you know, juicy little discussion about I mean the big things
to remind you that came up there were number one the major
question about היזק ראיה, hezek re'iah, number two the interesting question that
David just mentioned which is about can you do a קניין kinyan
to obligate yourself to do something? You can do a קניין kinyan
to create financial obligations but to obligate yourself to do an action
was an important side discussion in the גמרא. Another important discussion in
the גמרא which was a total digression was about taking, knocking down
a שול shul in order to build another one. Okay, and then
this whole like fascinating whole little thing about... about Herod. Okay, now
we get to another משנה Mishnah really on a completely different topic,
but it's also about building walls between people's yards, but really a
completely different concern. Let's take a look. המפיל. Hammapil. המקיף את חברו,
Hamakif et chaveiro, this might sound familiar to people from בבא קמא,
Bava Kamma, משלוש רוחותיו, mishalosh ruchotav, וגדר את הראשונה ואת השנייה ואת
השלישית, vegadar et harishona ve'et hashniya ve'et hashlishit, אין מחייבין אותו. ein
mechayvin oto. So basically you surround him, you have three fields that
surround his fields. Now you remember from the previous משנה Mishnah that
you cannot require a person to build a wall between fields, right?
Because there's no היזק ראיה, hezek re'iyah, you have no basis for
that. And so he was refusing to build a wall. So you
on your own initiative went ahead and built a wall, like we
saw in your own yard maybe, okay? אין מחייבין אותו, ein mechayvin
oto, so I can't make the guy pay for it. I was
doing it on my own. But now, what happens though, it only
says the first three walls you can't obligate because what's going to
happen is that after you build all four walls, right, imagine that
all of this is my property and that all of this is
ראובן's Reuven, property, and שמעון's got this yard in the middle. Okay,
if I build a wall here and here and here, he can
still say, look, buddy, you did it on your own, you couldn't
have obligated me, I'm not paying you a penny. But as soon
as I now build a wall here, I've actually helped him, not
for היזק ראיה hezek re'iyah where I don't have a legitimate claim
to do היזק ראיה hezek re'iyah or those types of issues out
in the middle of Iowa, in the middle of the wheat fields,
but that now his thing is surrounded by walls and it's protected
against animals and other things. So even though he didn't ask me,
this is like a classic case of יורד לתוך שדה חברו yored
letoch sadeh chaveiro where you go ahead and do some construction in
somebody else's yard that helps the person even if he didn't ask
you, and there's some sense that he has to, if not fully
reimburse you, at least reimburse you to some degree for the benefit
that you afforded him. So that's implicit. The משנה Mishnah says if
you do the first three, you don't make him pay, but it's
implicit that at the fourth one he would have to pay something.
Now the other thing by the way I should say is there's
an interesting debate back in בבא קמא Bava Kamma in the ראשונים
Rishonim about which walls are we talking about. The way I just
drew it it was these walls, but some say we're not talking
about those walls. We're talking about these walls. And you are building
walls just for yourself, but once you build the fourth wall, he's
now protected because he's in the middle. But someone can still trespass
into his field, like ראובן Reuven can trespass into שמעון's, but it
doesn't matter, we're not worried about trespass, we're worried about like animals
and other things. Okay, so anyway, let's just read it. Okay, Rabbi,
who built the fourth wall? So the משנה Mishnah is not clear.
The משנה says when you, the ראובן, Reuven build the first three,
you can't make him pay. The implication is that maybe when you
build the fourth you can make him pay. That's not spelled out,
but now let's see what רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi says. רבי יוסי
אומר אם עמד וגדר את הרביעית מגלגלין עליו את הכל. Rabbi Yosi
omer im amad vegadar et harevi'it megalgelin alav et hakol. If שמעון
got up and built the fourth wall, so now he protected himself
and he showed by the fact of building the fourth wall that
he really wants the walls, then you can now make him pay
for all the walls. Okay, now that's what רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi
says. What does the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma say? The תנא קמא
Tanna Kamma didn't address the case of a fourth wall. So let's
take a look at the גמרא.
אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל הלכה כרבי יוסי
Amar Rav Yehuda
amar
Shmuel halacha keRabbi Yosi we rule like רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi דאמר
de'amar who says אם עמד וגדר את הרביעית מגלגלין עליו
את הכל.
im amad vegadar et harevi'it megalgelin
alav et hakol. Then you can make him pay not fully, but
his portion because he now shows that he wants the walls. Now,
the גמרא has an important point. לא שנא עמד ניקף לא שנא
עמד מקיף. Lo shena amad nikaf lo shena amad makif.
And as opposed to the simple language of רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosi,
it
doesn't matter if ניקף, nikaf, the one being surrounded, שמעון, made
the wall, or
מקיף makif made the wall. Once the fourth wall is made, so
even if שמעון did not demonstrate through his actions that he wants
it, there's still a reality that he is now benefiting from the
protection by ראובן's walls.
So therefore ראובן can now
make him participate in the payment. Okay, so now it's like the
תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma. Right, well that's what the גמרא is going
to get to in the end.
The תנא קמא Tanna Kamma never directly addressed the case of the
fourth wall. Right, the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma by implication. Correct. איתמר
Itmar was said. רב הונא אמר הכל לפי מה שגדר. Rav Huna
amar hakol lefi mah shegadar. It's all based on what your costs.
If you built a brick wall or a stone wall, you make
him pay for half of a brick
wall, half of a stone wall. חייא בר רב אמר לא הכל
לפי דמי קנים בזול. Chiya bar Rav amar lo hakol lefi dmei
kanim bezol. He never agreed to be part of this
from the outset, it's only at the end and maybe he didn't
and then depending on how you read it, maybe even at the
end he didn't demonstrate his willingness, but even if he did demonstrate
his willingness at the end, he didn't participate from the beginning. So
you can make him pay for the benefit, but the benefit defined
on a very, like, minimal scale. So you built this nice strong
brick wall, you know, that cost like $10,000, and he said, yeah,
I wanted to be protected, but I would have bought a $1,000
stick wall. So you can make me pay for half of a
minimum wall, you can't make me I remember that I remember that
one of the first times that I was in college and I,
whatever, shared an apartment with people and cost like three hundred dollars
and they were like really upset. They said like, we wanted a
fifty dollar lock. So how much could I make them pay in
that case? Well, they told me to do it, but they didn't
specify. Anyway, so this is the guy, he says, I would have
got a small wall, so yes, I appreciate the wall, but I'm
not paying for the crazy thick wall you bought. What kind of
wall he put up? He put a nice brick wall up. All
right, so maybe it might depend. And even if he put up
a nice wall, maybe he put it up because it was consistent
with the other. Anyway, okay. רבי חייא חזי דמחייב קנים בזול. Rabbi
Chiyya Chazi Demichayev Kanim Bezol. All right, so I guess we're going
to have to end here and we will pick up tomorrow to
figure out A, how much does he contribute, and B, the question
of whether it depends and what the תנא קמא's Tanna Kamma's position
is, whether it depends if he built the fourth wall or if
the actual owner of the outside fields built the fourth wall. So
we will see all of that tomorrow.